Finding aid to the Sophia Smith Collection topical collection on women's health SSC.MS.00394
Sophia Smith Collection
Sophia Smith Collection topical collection on women's health
1860s-1980s
1818-2004
Sophia Smith Collection
SSC.MS.00394
3.75 linear feet (5 boxes)
An artificial collection documenting the evolution of medical and scientific thinking and practice relating to women's health. Topics include abortion, birth control, childbirth, eugenics, female genital mutilation, lactation, infant mortality, marriage instruction, mental hygiene, motherhood, nutrition, obstetrics, sexuality, sterilization, and AIDS. Types of materials include printed material, research materials, reports, and surveys.
Scope and Contents
This subject collection documents the evolution of medical and scientific thinking and practice relating to women's health from 1818-1990s. There are small amounts of material on such topics as abortion, birth control, childbirth, eugenics, female genital mutilation, lactation, infant mortality, marriage instruction, mental hygiene, motherhood, nutrition, obstetrics, sexuality, sterilization, and AIDS. Types of materials include articles, books, advertisements, clippings, research materials, reports, surveys, pamphlets, and newsletters from a wide range of authors ranging from misogynist to feminist.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series based on format, and alphabetically by topic or author thereunder.
Abortion--History; AIDS (Disease) in women; Birth control--History--20th century; Breast feeding--History; Childbirth--History; Child care--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Eugenics--History; Female circumcision--Developing countries; Infants--Mortality--History; Marriage--History; Nutrition--Women--History; Obstetrics--History; Sterilization (birth control)--History; Women--Health and hygiene--History; Women--Mental health--History; Women--Sexual behavior--History; Women's health services--History; Advertisements; articles; Books; clippings; Leaflets; Pamphlets; Publicity; Surveys; Research; reports; National Women's Health Network (U.S.)
- General resources, 1818-2004; 1
  - Articles, printed material (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Care of infants and children: pamphlets, 1926-28; undated (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  - Childbirth (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clinics
    - General (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Easter Women's Center, New York (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Feminist Women's Health Centers (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Women's Community Health Center, Cambridge (MA) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Vermont Women's Health Center, Burlington (VT); Women's Health Counseling Service, Springfield (MA); Women's Health Care Collective, Florence (MA); New Hampshire Feminist Health Center; Somerville (MA) Women's Health Center (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clitoridectomy: articles, 1818-1923; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Health Care system: articles, printed material (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hormone therapy: correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10a)
  - Maternity clothes: pamphlets, 1921-28; undated (Box 1, Folder 10b)
  - Menstruation: Kotex flyer and "Marjorie May's Twelfth Birthday" pamphlet, 1944; 1931 (Box 1, Folder 10b)
  - Organizations
    - Coalition for the Medical Rights of Women (Box 1, Folder 11)
      General
      [See also Periodicals: Second Opinion]
    - National Institute of Mental Health: Women's World (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - National Woman's Health Network (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Women's Health Forum (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pregnancy: pamphlets, 1926; undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Our Bodies Ourselves, ed. Boston Women's Health Collection 1st ed. (1970) and second printing (1971), 1970-71 (Box 1a, Folder 1)
    [see also books on shelf for later edition]
  - Surveys, research (Box 1a, Folder 2)
  - Women's Health Day: proceedings, 1980; 1991 (Box 1a, Folder 3)
  - Campaign for Women's Health, 1991 (Box 1a, Folder 4)
  - March for Women's Lives, 2004 (Box 1a, Folder 5)
  - Women and AIDS
    - Conference papers, published articles, reports (1-319) with index, 2 books, buttons, pamphlets, and stickers, 1980s-90s (Box 2)
    - Conference papers, published articles, and reports (Western Massachusetts focus), 1980s-90s (Box 3)
    - Conference papers, published articles, and reports (some New Jersey material), 1980s-90s (Box 4)
- Oversize materials, 1919-1979; 2
  - "Chart C: Overcoming weaknesses of women," Olympian System of exercises, 1919 (Box 5)
  - Feminist Women's Health Center (Los Angeles): miscellaneous printed materials, 1971-72 (Box 5)
  - "The Feminist Women's Health Center Report," Los Angeles Feminist Women's Health Center, undated issue and volume 1, number 2, 1975 (Box 5)
  - WomenWise the New Hampshire Feminist Health Center Quarterly, 1978-79 (Box 5)
- Books, 1871-1993; 3
  - Baker, Dorothy, All About the Yeast Beast, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Bissell, Mary Taylor, MD, Physical Development and Exercise for Women, 1891 (Box 5)
  - Blackwell, Antoinette Brown, Sexes Throughout Nature, 1875 (Box 5)
  - Boston Women's Health Collective (Box 4)
    - Our Bodies, Ourselves (2 editions), 1973; 1976 (Box 4)
    - The New Our Bodies Ourselves, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Cooke, Cynthia W., M.D. and Susan Dworkin, The Ms. Guide to a Woman's Healt h, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Duffey, Mrs. E.D., What Women Should Know, 1884 (Box 4)
  - Ehrenreich, Barbara and Deirdre English, Complaints and Disorders: The Sexual Politics of Sickness, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Haynes, Jim and Palse-Green, Jeanne, Hello I Love You, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Hosken, Fran, Female Sexual Mutilations: The Facts and Proposals for Action. An Action Guide. (Lexington, MA. Women's International Network News), 1980 (Box 4)
  - Hosken, Fran. The Hosken Report, Genital and Sexual Mutilation of Females, (Second enlarged edition. Lexington, MA. Women's International Network News, and Fourth edition), 1979; 1993 (Box 4)
  - Lane, William, Safer Motherhood, 1934 (Box 5)
  - Lowry, E.B. Dr., Confidences: Tales from a Young Girl Concerning Herself, 1919 (Box 5)
  - MacKeith, Nancy, ed., The New Women's Health Handbook. (London, Virago, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Napheys, George H., The Physical Life of Woman: Advice to the Maiden, Wife, and Mother 1871 (pages missing; 2 copies) (Box 5)
  - Pancoast, S., et al., Beautiful Womanhood Guide to Mental and Physical Development, 1905